Afonso Braga De Alcantara

Cloud Solutions Architecture | 4x AWS Certified | Cloud-native architecture enthusiast

Address São Paulo, 04605003 SP LinkedIn: linkedin.com/in/afonsoalcantara/

Phone +55 11 98431-7446

E-mail alcantara.afonso@gmail.com

IT Solution Architecture and a Serverless and ReactJS architecture enthusiast.

IT Solution and Enterprise Architecture professional, over 10 years of experience, with emphasis on insurance and bank operations.

Professional graduated in Computer Science from Universidade Anhembi Morumbi and with a postgraduate degree in Information Technology Governance from PUC. Strong acting in SOA projects, integration, and serverless architecture. Business envisioning applied to strategic IT, contract management, and outsourcing providers.

Tech leader with a focus on knowledge multiplication, the delegation of activities, and negotiation.

Strong knowledge of ITIL, SCRUM RUP, TOGAF, Middlewares, ESB, SOA methodology, AWS Cloud (Microservices and serverless architecture), and ReactJS.

Experience in development projects of solution architecture and corporate teams, Mobile development, application of insurance quote, and contracting and implementation of software development methodologies.

Skills

Enterprise Architecture	Very Good
IT Solution Architecture	Excellent
Serverless Architecture	Excellent
Insurance and bank products	Good
IT Governance	Good
Digital Transformation Projects	Very Good
Systemic envisioning	Excellent
Experience in international project	Very Good
Results-driven	Excellent
Multidisciplinary Projects	



Work History

2023-08 - Current

Solution Architecture Specialist

Porto Seguro – Insurance Company, São Paulo – SP Development of solutions for applications that supports Automobile insurance (Quotation and Issuance) operation. All solutions are based on AWS Technologies integrated with legacy technology used at Porto.

Main deliverables:

 Working on M&As processes being responsible for technical due diligence.

2023-03 - 2023-08

Sr. Solution Architect

Itaú Unibanco – Financial Company, São Paulo - SP

Development of solutions for applications that supports PIX's operation. All solutions were based on AWS Technologies.

2021-05 - 2023-03

IT Solution Architect Specialist

DASA – Health Company, São Paulo - SP

Development of solutions for applications and project development, Support with technical knowledge to squads of the Patient and CRM Journeys

Main deliverables:

- Acting on the Software Selection process focused on tools to support DASA's Ecosystem. The milestone of this process was the selection of Google CCAI as a virtual assistant.
- Definition of customer service reference architecture which combines Twilio/SalesForce ServiceCloud, and CCAI.
- Setting up CCAI's development guide.

2018-08 - 2021-04

IT Solution Architecture Manager

MAPFRE INSURANCE, São Paulo - SP

Managing the architecture area involves overseeing routine administration, developing solutions for applications and projects, managing service providers, and leading a team. Additionally, it includes developing reference architecture and DevOps strategies. I am also a member of the Global Architecture Committee at Mapfre. Main deliverables:

 Support for application development projects that serve the Core Business with technical definitions and knowledge of the support

- systems and how to integrate with them
- Definition and implementation of the ALM strategy to meet the agile and traditional methodologies, redefining the source code repositories, integration pipelines, and deploys
- Acting in defining architecture building blocks and their documentation and in creating the architecture repository, centralizing their artefacts, models, and guides
- Acting in definition, working with the Global Enterprise Architecture area in Spain, the SAM architecture adopted for Cloud projects
- Development of an application using ReactJS stack in the frontend based on Flux Architecture
- The Backends' architecture is Cloud Native and all the microservices are designed with a Domain-Driven Design approach
- The back-end is hosted on AWS and developed using services Lambda (NodeJS), Cognito, SNS (To integrate the services whenever necessary), DynamoDB, Route 53, CloudFront AWS Certificate Manager, and S3, to support the back-end's operations
- Development of a PoC of AWS Alexa Skills.

2014-03 - 2018-08

IT Solution Architecture Manager

BBMAPFRE INSURANCE GROUP, São Paulo - SP

Managing the architecture area by overseeing daily operations, developing solutions for applications, managing service providers, leading teams, and serving as a member of the Global Architecture Committee at Mapfre.

- Management of service providers
- Leadership team
- Member of the Global Architecture committee at MAPFRE Main deliverables:
- Development and implementation of the Corporate Wiki, an internal tool that concentrates and makes available to employees' corporate information regarding the Technology and Business areas, such as systems, servers, project documentation, architecture, topology, and integrations
- To support in projects for the development of applications for assistance requests and the opening of claims notices, which is part of the Group's Digital Transformation strategy, with technical definitions and knowledge of legacy systems and how to integrate with them
- Attendance, working together with the architectural area of

MAPFRE Spain, in definition of GAIA architecture (Global Architecture for Insurance Applications), which is oriented towards microservices

- The Front-end is composed by Angular JS 2, Yeoman, Grunt, Karma, NodeJS and Java, and Spring as the Backend
- Performance of the implementation of the MUM development methodology, used in MAPFRE Spain, based on the RUP
- Definition and implementation of the Group's continuous integration strategy, supported by Jenkins, Artifactory, JUnit, Selenium, and SonarQube tools
- Acting in defining architecture building blocks and their documentation and in creating the architecture repository, centralizing their artifacts, models, and guides.

2011-09 - 2014-03 Sr. Solution Architect

BBMAPFRE INSURANCE GROUP, São Paulo - SP

Development of solutions for applications, development of SOA methodology, and canonical model

Main deliverables:

- Development and implementation of the SOA methodology and definition and construction of the canonical model
- Acting in the definition and execution of the restructuring of the service bus development, approval, and production environments (SAG WebMethods) and the creation of its governance model and the definition of the Group's integration standards
- Definition and construction of the Group's technological matrix
- Development of a proof of concepts for the adoption of new technologies, documentation of these in the technological matrix, as well as the definition of their applicability scenarios
- Acting in defining architecture building blocks and their documentation and in creating the architecture repository, centralizing their artifacts, models, and guides.

2010-04 - 2011-08 Sr. Developer

THOMSON REUTERS ONESOURCE, MASTERSAF, São Paulo - SP

Responsible for developing Mastersaf's product interface integrations with Oracle EBS.

Main Deliverables:

- Definition of the EFD PIS / COFINS project architecture, using the Scrum methodology for project development
- Development of several POCs, with emphasis on the BI tool, later adopted by Mastersaf
- Projects were developed in Java EE and the Kettle framework of

Pentaho BI

 Definition and implementation of Confluence (Wiki Corporativo), to aggregate information from the project areas and have an alignment regarding the projects and strategies they have adopted.

2009-04 - 2010-02 SOA Architect / Partner Owner

ITValue - IT, São Paulo - SP

The idealization of the company and opening up to society.

Development of business plan, lead capture project, and respective presentation to the investor group, until further absorption by Mastersaf.

Main Deliverables:

- Acted as an Oracle instructor responsible for Oracle Application Server, Oracle BPEL, Oracle ESB, Oracle XML Fundamentals, Oracle BAM, Oracle Portal, and SOA Essentials courses, on the 10g platform
- Worked in implementation of Oracle EBS R12 integration projects with the Mastersaf DW product, using Oracle BPEL and adapters
- Worked in Java JEE development projects for integration with ERP IFS, exposing information via WebServices
- Worked in company administration, fundraising in the market, and prospecting for new customers.

2007-08 - 2009-04 SOA Architect

Resource IT Solutions, São Paulo - SP

Responsible for providing consultancy as an SOA architect for clients, focusing on the financial segment.

Main Deliveries:

- Worked in the creation and implementation of the Agility methodology in the Redecard client (known today as Rede)
- Contemplating from the modeling of services, creation of the reference architecture, to development of the project
- Later implementation of the pilot, coordinating a team of 5 (five) people, using Oracle Application Server 10g, Oracle BPEL 10g, Oracle ESB 10g, and Oracle BAM products
- Worked in the Installation of Oracle SOA Suite, WebServices
 Manager, Oracle GridControl, and Oracle BAM products on the
 installation platform for development, quality, and production
 servers environment on the Claro Telefonica client.

Education

2023-10 - 2024-11 MBA: Cloud Engineering & Architecture

FIAP - São Paulo - SP, Brazil

2017-07 - 2018-12 Postgraduate Degree: Information Technology

Governance

Pontifícia Universidade Católica - PUC - São Paulo - SP, Brazil

2011-01 - 2014-12 Bachelor of Applied Science in Information

Technology: Computer Science

Universidade Anhembi Morumbi - São Paulo - SP, Brazil

1996-01 - 1998-12 Technician Degree: Data Processing

Instituto Batista Do Amazonas - Manaus - AM, Brazil

Courses

- Inteligência Competitiva e Cognitiva com uso de IBM cloud e Watson, Shift Fiap;
- Gestão de Contratos e Fornecedores, Universidade Corporativa BBMapfre;
- Desenvolvimento móvel com Google Android, Caelum;
- Desenvolvimento móvel com iOS, Caleum;
- Introdução ao BigData, FIA;
- General English, EC London

Certifications

2024-03	AWS Certified SysOps Administrator - Associate
2023-10	<u>EF SET Certificate – C2</u>
2022-10	AWS Certified Solutions Architect - Associate
2021-09	AWS Certified Developer - Associate
2018-10	AWS Certified Cloud Practitioner
2017-12	Agile Scrum Foundation Certificate, Exin
2017-06	TOGAF 9 Foundation, The OpenGroup
2014-12	ITIL® Foundation Certificate in IT Service Management, Exin
2007-12	Sun Certified Web Component Developer for J2EE 1.4, Sun MicroSystens/Oracle
2004-12	Sun Certified Java Programmer for Java 2 Platform, Standard Edition

1.4, Sun MicroSystens/Oracle

Languages

Brazilian Portuguese

Excellent

English

Very Good

Spanish

Good

Additional Information

- Single. Availability for travel.
- Attendance to Executive Briefing Center Event, at Microsoft headquarter, Seattle, WA.
- Attendance to Software AG Innovation World Event, San Francisco, CA.
- Student exchange program to improve the English language, London, EN.

Published Articles

<u>Titanic's complex: The challenge of big companies</u>

Using Serverless Framework and AWS for the first time

Serverless Framework and AWS - Part II

AWS Cloud Development Kit - CDK

<u>Understanding asynchronousness and its Patterns in JavaScript</u>

<u>CloudWatch + OpenSearch + Kibana</u>

Architecture patterns

Amazon Lex

Implementing Clean Architecture with SpringBoot

<u>LocalStack — AWS in your machine and for free. It's a dream come</u> true.

AWS CodeWhisperer and Github Copilot, which one is better?

A step-by-step guide to running a Python Docker Image on AWS

Lambda